Hello and welcome.
In this video, we will learn
a machine learning method called,
Support Vector Machine, or SVM,
which is used for classification.
So let's get started.
Imagine that you've obtained
a dataset containing characteristics
of thousands of human cell samples
extracted from patients who were believed
to be at risk of developing cancer.
Analysis of the original data showed that
many of the characteristics differed
significantly between benign and
malignant samples.
You can use the values of
these cell characteristics
in samples from other patients,
to give an early indication of whether
a new sample might be benign or malignant.
You can use Support Vector Machine, or
SVM, as a classifier
to train your model to
understand patterns within the data that
might show, benign or malignant cells.
Once the model has been trained,
it can be used to predict your new or
unknown cell with rather high accuracy.
Now, let me give you
a formal definition of SVM.
A Support Vector Machine
is a supervised algorithm
that can classify cases
by finding a separator.
SVM works by first mapping data to a high
dimensional feature space so that data
points can be categorized, even when the
data are not otherwise linearly separable.
Then, a separator is estimated for
the data.
The data should be
transformed in such a way
that a separator could be
drawn as a hyperplane.
For example, consider the following
figure, which shows the distribution of
a small set of cells only based on
their unit size and clump thickness.
As you can see, the data points
fall into two different categories.
It represents a linearly
non separable data set.
The two categories can be separated
with a curve but not a line.
That is, it represents a linearly
non separable data set,
which is the case for
most real world data sets.
We can transfer this data to
a higher-dimensional space, for
example, mapping it to
a three-dimensional space.
After the transformation,
the boundary between the two categories
can be defined by a hyperplane.
As we are now in three-dimensional space,
the separator is shown as a plane.
This plane can be used to classify new or
unknown cases.
Therefore, the SVM algorithm
outputs an optimal hyperplane
that categorizes new examples.
Now, there are two challenging
questions to consider.
First, how do we transfer
data in such a way
that a separator could be
drawn as a hyperplane?
And two, how can we find the best or
optimized hyperplane separator
after transformation?
Let's first look at transforming
data to see how it works.
For the sake of simplicity, imagine that
our dataset is one-dimensional data.
This means we have only one feature x.
As you can see,
it is not linearly separable.
So what can we do here?
Well, we can transfer it into
a two-dimensional space.
For example, you can increase
the dimension of data by mapping x into
a new space using a function
with outputs x and x squared.
Now the data is linearly separable, right?
Notice that as we are in a two-dimensional
space, the hyperplane is a line
dividing a plane into two parts where
each class lays on either side.
Now we can use this line
to classify new cases.
Basically, mapping data into
a higher-dimensional space is called,
kernelling.
The mathematical function used for
the transformation is known as the kernel
function, and can be of different types,
such as linear,
polynomial, Radial Basis Function,
or RBF, and sigmoid.
Each of these functions has its own
characteristics, its pros and cons, and
its equation.
But the good news is that you don't
need to know them as most of them
are already implemented in libraries
of data science programming languages.
Also, as there's no easy way of knowing
which function performs best with any
given dataset, we usually choose different
functions in turn and compare the results.
Now we get to another question.
Specifically, how do we find the right or
optimized separator after transformation?
Basically, SVMs are based on
the idea of finding a hyperplane
that best divides a data set
into two classes as shown here.
As we're in a two-dimensional space,
you can think of the hyperplane
as a line that linearly separates
the blue points from the red points.
One reasonable choice as the best
hyperplane is the one that represents
the largest separation or
margin between the two classes.
So the goal is to choose a hyperplane
with as big a margin as possible.
Examples closest to the hyperplane
are support vectors.
It is intuitive that only support
vectors matter for achieving our goal.
And thus,
other trending examples can be ignored.
We tried to find the hyperplane
in such a way that
it has the maximum distance
to support vectors.
Please note that the hyperplane and
boundary decision lines,
have their own equations.
So finding the optimized hyperplane can
be formalized using an equation which
involves quite a bit more math, so I'm not
going to go through it here in detail.
That said, the hyperplane is
learned from training data
using an optimization procedure
that maximizes the margin.
And like many other problems,
this optimization problem can
also be solved by gradient descent,
which is out of scope of this video.
Therefore, the output of the algorithm
is the values w and b for the line.
You can make classifications
using this estimated line.
It is enough to plug in input
values into the line equation.
Then, you can calculate whether an unknown
point is above or below the line.
If the equation returns
a value greater than 0,
then the point belongs to the first class
which is above the line, and vice-versa.
The two main advantages of support
vector machines are that they're
accurate in high-dimensional spaces.
And they use a subset of training
points in the decision function called,
support vectors, so
it's also memory efficient.
The disadvantages of
Support Vector Machines
include the fact that
the algorithm is prone for
over-fitting if the number of features is
much greater than the number of samples.
Also, SVMs do not directly
provide probability estimates,
which are desirable in most
classification problems.
And finally, SVMs are not very
efficient computationally
if your dataset is very big, such as
when you have more than 1,000 rows.
And now our final question is,
in which situation should I use SVM?
Well, SVM is good for
image analysis tasks,
such as image classification and
hand written digit recognition.
Also, SVM is very effective
in text mining tasks,
particularly due to its effectiveness
in dealing with high-dimensional data.
For example, it is used for
detecting spam, text category
assignment and sentiment analysis.
Another application of SVM is in
gene expression data classification,
again, because of its power in
high-dimensional data classification.
SVM can also be used for
other types of machine learning problems,
such as regression,
outlier detection and clustering.
I'll leave it to you to explore more
about these particular problems.
This concludes this video,
thanks for watching.