All right, before we start
learning about foursquare and
their API, let's get some of
the logistics out of the way.
For this project, we will be using
Watson Studio as the platform
to build our code for the project and
to share it with our peers.
So each of you will need to
create a Watson Studio account
in order to proceed with the course.
And in this video I will walk
you through the process.
Now for those you who don't know,
Watson Studio is an awesome platform that
provides a suite of tools for data
other scientists to collaboratively and
easily work with application developers,
and subject matter experts.
And to build, train, and
deploy models at scale.
For the sake of this project, we won't
be doing any extensive machine learning.
But by using Watson Studio and
learning about its features, you will
hopefully appreciate what it has to offer.
So let's go to the following link that is
www.ibm.com/cloud/watson-studio.
This will take you to the landing
page of Watson Studio.
Feel free to check it out to
learn more about its features and
what the platform has to offer.
You can also watch the video
to learn more about it.
And once you're ready
to create an account,
you can simply click on
Start your free trial.
This will bring you to a page where
you have to enter your email address.
So I'm going to do that.
And then check the box
to accept the terms.
Once you've done that, click Next.
This will redirect you to a page where you
have to fill in your personal details.
So go ahead and fill in your First and
Last Name, your Country or
Region, and a password for your account.
Then you can check the box if you wish
to remain informed about any products or
services by IBM.
And then scroll down and
click Create Account.
Awesome, so at this point, you should
receive an email to confirm your account
and to continue with this kind of process.
So go to your account and
follow the instructions in the email.
I'm going to do the same thing here.
[SOUND] By the way,
this is just a dummy account
that I created for demonstration purposes.
There you go.
Here is the email from IBM Cloud.
So you click on the email and
you click Confirm Account.
Awesome.
You should automatically then
get redirected to this page.
Now this page has all the details
about the IBM privacy policy, so
feel free to read it to understand
the policy and your rights as a user.
Then scroll down all the way to
the bottom and click proceed.
Here you can specify what account
to use and the organization.
And the IBM cloud space,
in case you have more than one.
But for most of you, you can simply
go with the default settings, so
just click Continue.
Right now we'll take some
time to create your account.
There you go.
And that completes the process
of signing up on Watson Studio.
Now you can click Get Started.
Once you get to this page,
you're good to go and
you're good to start
creating new projects.
Now in the next video,
I'll show you how to create a project and
how to start creating notebooks
under that project and
how to share them with your peers or
other collaborators.
So I'll see you in the next video.