Hello and welcome.
In this video,
we'll be covering linear regression.
You don't need to know any linear algebra
to understand topics in linear regression.
This high-level introduction will give you
enough background information on linear
regression to be able to use it
effectively on your own problems.
So let's get started.
Let's take a look at this data set.
It's related to the Co2
emission of different cars.
It includes engine size,
cylinders, fuel consumption and
Co2 emissions for various car models.
The question is, given this data set,
can we predict the Co2 emission of a car
using another field such as engine size?
Quite simply, yes.
We can use linear regression
to predict a continuous value
such as Co2 emission by
using other variables.
Linear regression is
the approximation of a linear model
used to describe the relationship
between two or more variables.
In simple linear regression,
there are two variables,
a dependent variable and
an independent variable.
The key point in the linear regression
is that our dependent value should be
continuous and cannot be a discrete value.
However, the independent variables can
be measured on either a categorical or
continuous measurement scale.
There are two types of
linear regression models.
They are simple regression and
multiple regression.
Simple linear regression is when
one independent variable is used
to estimate a dependent variable.
For example, predicting Co2 emission
using the engine size variable.
When more than one independent variable
is present the process is called
multiple linear regression, for example,
predicting Co2 emission using
engine size and cylinders of cars.
Our focus in this video is
on simple linear regression.
Now let's see how linear regression works.
Okay, so let's look at our data set again.
To understand linear regression,
we can plot our variables here.
We show engine size as
an independent variable and
emission as the target value
that we would like to predict.
A scatter plot clearly shows the relation
between variables where changes in
one variable explain or possibly
cause changes in the other variable.
Also, it indicates that these
variables are linearly related.
With linear regression you can
fit a line through the data.
For instance, as the engine size
increases, so do the emissions.
With linear regression you can model
the relationship of these variables.
A good model can be used to predict what
the approximate emission of each car is.
How do we use this line for
prediction now?
Let us assume for a moment that
the line is a good fit of the data.
We can use it to predict
the emission of an unknown car.
For example, for
a sample car with engine size 2.4,
you can find the emission is 214.
Now, let's talk about what
the fitting line actually is.
We're going to predict the target value y.
In our case using the independent
variable engine size represented by x1.
The fit line is shown
traditionally as a polynomial.
In a simple regression problem,
a single x,
the form of the model would
be theta 0 plus theta 1 x1.
In this equation, y hat is the dependent
variable of the predicted value.
And x1 is the independent variable.
Theta 0 and theta 1 are the parameters
of the line that we must adjust.
Theta 1 is known as the slope or
gradient of the fitting line and
theta 0 is known as the intercept.
Theta 0 and theta 1 are also called
the coefficients of the linear equation.
You can interpret this
equation as y hat being
a function of x1, or
y hat being dependent of x1.
How would you draw a line
through the points?
And how do you determine
which line fits best?
Linear regression estimates
the coefficients of the line.
This means we must calculate theta 0 and
theta 1 to find the best
line to fit the data.
This line would best estimate
the emission of the unknown data points.
Let's see how we can find this line or,
to be more precise,
how we can adjust the parameters to
make the line the best fit for the data.
For a moment, let's assume we've already
found the best fit line for our data.
Now, let's go through all the points and
check how well they align with this line.
Best fit here means that if we have,
for instance,
a car with engine size x1 = 5.4 and
actual Co2 = 250,
its Co2 should be predicted
very close to the actual value,
which is y = 250 based on historical data.
But if we use the fit line,
or better to say
using our polynomial with known
parameters to predict the Co2 emission,
it will return y hat = 340.
Now if you compare the actual value
of the emission of the car with what
we've predicted using our model, you will
find out that we have a 90 unit error.
This means our prediction
line is not accurate.
This error is also called
the residual error.
So we can say the error is
the distance from the data point
to the fitted regression line.
The mean of all residual errors
shows how poorly the line
fits with the whole data set.
Mathematically it can be shown by the
equation Mean Squared Error, shown as MSE.
Our objective is to find a line where
the mean of all these errors is minimized.
In other words,
the mean error of the prediction using
the fit line should be minimized.
Let's reword it more technically.
The objective of linear regression,
is to minimize this MSE equation and
to minimize it, we should find the best
parameters theta 0 and theta 1.
Now the question is,
how to find theta 0 and
theta 1 In such a way that
it minimizes this error?
How can we find such a perfect line?
Or said another way, how should we
find the best parameters for our line?
Should we move the line a lot randomly and
calculate the MSE value every time and
choose the minimum one?
Not really.
Actually, we have two options here.
Option one,
we can use a mathematic approach, or
option two,
we can use an optimization approach.
Let's see how we could easily use a
mathematic formula to find the theta 0 and
theta 1.
As mentioned before, theta 0 and
theta 1 in the simple linear regression
are the coefficients of the fit line.
We can use a simple equation to
estimate these coefficients.
That is, given that it's a simple linear
regression with only two parameters,
and knowing that theta 0 and
theta 1 are the intercept and
slope of the line, we can estimate
them directly from our data.
It requires that we calculate the mean
of the independent and dependent or
target columns from the data set.
Notice that all of the data must
be available to traverse and
calculate the parameters.
It can be shown that the intercept and
slope can be calculated
using these equations.
We can start off by estimating
the value for theta 1.
This is how you can find the slope
of a line based on the data.
X bar is the average value for
the engine size in our data set.
Please consider that we have
nine rows here, rows 0 to 8.
First we calculate the average of x1 and
average of y,
then we plug it into the slope
equation to find theta 1.
The xi and yi in the equation
refer to the fact that we
need to repeat these calculations
across all values in our data set.
And i refers to the ith value of x or y.
Applying all values,
we find theta 1 equals 39.
It is our second parameter.
It is used to calculate
the first parameter
which is the intercept of the line.
Now we can plug theta 1 into
the line equation to find theta 0.
It is easily calculated
that theta 0 equals 125.74.
So these are the two parameters for
the line,
where theta 0 is also called
the bias coefficient, and
theta 1 is the coefficient for
the Co2 emission column.
As a side note, you really don't
need to remember the formula for
calculating these parameters, as most of
the libraries used for machine learning
in Python, R and Scala can easily
find these parameters for you.
But it's always good to
understand how it works.
Now, we can write down
the polynomial of the line.
So we know how to find the best fit for
our data and its equation.
Now the question is how can we use it
to predict the emission of a new car
based on its engine size?
After we found the parameters
of the linear equation,
making predictions is as simple as solving
the equation for a specific set of inputs.
Imagine we are predicting Co2 emission,
or y,
from engine size, or x for
the automobile in record number 9.
Our linear regression
model representation for
this problem would be y hat
= theta 0 + theta 1 x1.
Or if we map it to our data set,
it would be Co2Emission =
theta 0 + theta 1 EngineSize.
As we saw, we can find theta 0,
theta 1 using the equations
that we just talked about.
Once found, we can plug in
the equation of the linear model.
For example, let's use theta 0 = 125 and
theta 1 = 39.
So we can rewrite the linear
model as Co2Emission
equals 125 plus 39 EngineSize.
Now let's plug in the 9th
row of our data set and
calculate the Co2 emission for
a car with an engine size of 2.4.
So Co2Emission = 125 + 39 x 2.4.
Therefore, we can predict
that the Co2Emission for
this specific car would be 218.6.
Let's talk a bit about why
linear regression is so useful.
Quite simply it is the most basic
regression to use and understand.
In fact, one reason why linear regression
is so useful is that it's fast.
It also doesn't require
tuning of parameters.
So something like tuning the K
parameter and K nearest neighbors, or
the learning rate in neural networks
isn't something to worry about.
Linear regression is also easy to
understand, and highly interpretable.
Thanks for watching this video.