Hello and welcome.
In this video, we'll be covering more
details about hierarchical clustering.
Let's get started.
Let's look at agglomerative algorithm for
hierarchical clustering.
Remember that agglomerative
clustering is a bottom up approach.
Let's say our data set has n data points.
First, we want to create n clusters,
one for each data point.
Then, each point is assigned as a cluster.
Next, we want to compute
the distance proximity matrix
which will be an n by n table.
After that, we want to iteratively run
the following steps until the specified
cluster number is reached, or
until there is only one cluster left.
First, merge the two nearest clusters.
Distances are computed already
in the proximity matrix.
Second, update the proximity
matrix with the new values.
We stop after we've reached
the specified number of clusters, or
there is only one cluster remaining
with the result stored in a dendogram.
So in the proximity matrix, we have to
measure the distances between clusters and
also merge the clusters that are nearest.
So, the key operation is the computation
of the proximity between
the clusters with one point and
also clusters with multiple data points.
At this point, there are a number of
key questions that need to be answered.
For instance, how do we measure
the distances between these clusters and
how do we define
the nearest among clusters?
We also can ask, which points do we use?
First, let's see how to calculate
the distance between two clusters
with one point each.
Let's assume that we have
a data set of patients and
we want to cluster them
using hierarchy clustering.
So our data points are patients with
a featured set of three dimensions.
For example, age, body mass index,
or BMI and blood pressure.
We can use different distance measurements
to calculate the proximity matrix.
For instance, Euclidean distance.
So, if we have a data set of n patience,
we can billed an n by n
dissimilarity distance matrix.
It will give us the distance of
clusters with one data point.
However, as mentioned, we merge
clusters in agglomerative clustering.
Now the question is, how can we
calculate the distance between clusters
when there are multiple
patients in each cluster?
We can use different criteria to find
the closest clusters and merge them.
In general, it completely depends on
the data type, dimensionality of data and
most importantly,
the domain knowledge of the data set.
In fact, different approaches to
defining the distance between clusters
distinguish the different algorithms.
As you might imagine,
there are multiple ways we can do this.
The first one is called
single linkage clustering.
Single linkage is defined as the shortest
distance between two points in
each cluster, such as point a and b.
Next up is complete linkage clustering.
This time we are finding the longest
distance between the points in
each cluster, such as the distance
between point a and b.
The third type of linkage is average
linkage clustering or the mean distance.
This means we're looking at the average
distance of each point from one cluster
to every point in another cluster.
The final linkage type to be reviewed
is centroid linkage clustering.
Centroid is the average of the feature
sets of points in a cluster.
This linkage takes into account
the centroid of each cluster
when determining the minimum distance.
There are three main advantages
to using hierarchical clustering.
First, we do not need to specify
the number of clusters required for
the algorithm.
Second, hierarchical clustering
is easy to implement.
And third, the dendrogram produced is
very useful in understanding the data.
There are some disadvantages as well.
First, the algorithm can never
undo any previous steps.
So for example,
the algorithm clusters two points and
later on, we see that
the connection was not a good one.
The program can not undo that step.
Second, the time complexity for
the clustering can result in very long
computation times in comparison with
efficient algorithms such as K-means.
Finally, if we have a large data set,
it can become difficult to determine
the correct number of
clusters by the dendrogram.
Now, lets compare hierarchical
clustering with K-means.
K-means is more efficient for
large data sets.
In contrast to K-means,
hierarchical clustering does not require
the number of cluster to be specified.
Hierarchical clustering gives more
than one partitioning depending on
the resolution or as K-means gives
only one partitioning of the data.
Hierarchical clustering always
generates the same clusters,
in contrast with K-means, that returns
different clusters each time it is run,
due to random initialization of centroids.
Thanks for watching.