Hello and welcome.
In this video, we'll look at k-Means
accuracy and characteristics.
Let's get started.
Let's define the algorithm
more concretely,
before we talk about its accuracy.
A k-Means algorithm works by randomly
placing k centroids, one for each cluster.
The farther apart the clusters are placed,
the better.
The next step is to calculate
the distance of each data point or
object from the centroids.
Euclidean distance is used to measure the
distance from the object to the centroid.
Please note, however,
that you can also use
different types of distance measurements,
not just Euclidean distance.
Euclidean distance is used
because it's the most popular.
Then, assign each data point or object to
its closest centroid creating a group.
Next, once each data point has
been classified to a group,
recalculate the position
of the k centroids.
The new centroid position is determined
by the mean of all points in the group.
Finally, this continues until
the centroids no longer move.
Now, the questions is,
how can we evaluate the goodness
of the clusters formed by k-Means?
In other words, how do we calculate
the accuracy of k-Means clustering?
One way is to compare the clusters with
the ground truth, if it's available.
However, because k-Means is
an unsupervised algorithm
we usually don't have ground truth
in real world problems to be used.
But there is still a way to
say how bad each cluster is,
based on the objective of the k-Means.
This value is the average distance
between data points within a cluster.
Also, average of the distances of data
points from their cluster centroids
can be used as a metric of error for
the clustering algorithm.
Essentially, determining the number
of clusters in a data set, or
k as in the k-Means algorithm,
is a frequent problem in data clustering.
The correct choice of K is often ambiguous
because it's very dependent on the shape
and scale of the distribution
of points in a dataset.
There are some approaches to
address this problem, but
one of the techniques that is commonly
used is to run the clustering across
the different values of K and looking
at a metric of accuracy for clustering.
This metric can be mean, distance between
data points and their cluster's centroid.
Which indicate how dense
our clusters are or,
to what extent we minimize
the error of clustering.
Then, looking at the change of this
metric, we can find the best value for K.
But the problem is that with
increasing the number of clusters,
the distance of centroids to
data points will always reduce.
This means increasing K will
always decrease the error.
So, the value of the metric as
a function of K is plotted and
the elbow point is determined where
the rate of decrease sharply shifts.
It is the right K for clustering.
This method is called the elbow method.
So let's recap k-Means clustering.
k-Means is a partition-based
clustering which is A,
relatively efficient on medium and
large sized data sets.
B, produces sphere-like
clusters because the clusters
are shaped around the centroids.
And C, its drawback is that we should
pre-specify the number of clusters,
and this is not an easy task.
Thanks for watching.