Hello and welcome. In this video,
we'll learn a machine learning method called
Logistic Regression which is used for classification.
In examining this method,
we'll specifically answer these three questions.
What is logistic regression?
What kind of problems can be solved by logistic regression?
In which situations do we use logistic regression? So let's get started.
Logistic regression is a statistical and machine learning technique for
classifying records of a dataset based on the values of the input fields.
Let's say we have a telecommunication dataset that we'd like to
analyze in order to understand which customers might leave us next month.
This is historical customer data where each row represents one customer.
Imagine that you're an analyst at this company
and you have to find out who is leaving and why?
You'll use the dataset to build a model based on
historical records and use it to predict the future churn within the customer group.
The dataset includes information about services that
each customer has signed up for, customer account information,
demographic information about customers like gender and
age range and also customers who've left the company within the last month.
The column is called churn.
We can use logistic regression to build a model for
predicting customer churn using the given features.
In logistic regression, we use one or more independent variables such as tenure,
age and income to predict an outcome, such as churn,
which we call the dependent variable
representing whether or not customers will stop using the service.
Logistic regression is analogous to linear regression,
but tries to predict a categorical or discrete target field instead of a numeric one.
In linear regression, we might try to predict
a continuous value of variables such as the price of a house,
blood pressure of a patient,
or fuel consumption of a car.
But in logistic regression,
we predict a variable which is binary such as yes/no, true/false,
successful or not successful, pregnant/not pregnant,
and so on, all of which can be coded as zero or one.
In logistic regression dependent variables should be continuous.
If categorical, they should be dummy or indicator coded.
This means we have to transform them to some continuous value.
Please note that logistic regression can be used for
both binary classification and multi-class classification.
But for simplicity in this video,
we'll focus on binary classification.
Let's examine some applications of logistic regression before we explain how they work.
As mentioned, logistic regression is a type of classification algorithm,
so it can be used in different situations.
For example, to predict the probability of a person
having a heart attack within a specified time period,
based on our knowledge of the person's age,
sex and body mass index.
Or to predict the chance of mortality and
an injured patient or to predict whether a patient has
a given disease such as diabetes based on
observed characteristics of that patient such as weight,
height, blood pressure and results of various blood tests and so on.
In a marketing context,
we can use it to predict the likelihood of a customer purchasing
a product or halting a subscription as we've done in our churn example.
We can also use logistic regression to predict
the probability of failure of a given process, system or product.
We can even use it to predict the likelihood of a homeowner defaulting on a mortgage.
These are all good examples of problems that can be solved using logistic regression.
Notice that in all these examples not only do we predict the class of each case,
we also measure the probability of a case belonging to a specific class.
There are different machine algorithms which can classify or estimate a variable.
The question is, when should we use logistic regression?
Here are four situations in which logistic regression is a good candidate.
First, when the target field in your data is categorical or specifically is binary.
Such as zero/one, yes/no,
churn or no churn, positive/negative and so on.
Second, you need the probability of your prediction.
For example, if you want to know what the probability is of a customer buying a product.
Logistic regression returns a probability score
between zero and one for a given sample of data.
In fact, logistic regression predicts the probability of
that sample and we map the cases to a discrete class based on that probability.
Third, if your data is linearly separable.
The decision boundary of logistic regression is a line or a plane or a hyper plane.
A classifier will classify all the points on
one side of the decision boundary as belonging to one class,
and all those on the other side as belonging to the other class.
For example, if we have just two features and they're
not applying any polynomial processing we can obtain
an inequality like Theta zero plus Theta 1x1 plus theta 2x2 is greater than zero,
which is a half-plane easily plotable.
Please note that in using logistic regression,
we can also achieve a complex decision boundary using polynomial processing as well,
which is out of scope here you'll get more insight from
decision boundaries when you understand how logistic regression works.
Fourth, you need to understand the impact of a feature.
You can select the best features based on
the statistical significance of the logistic regression model coefficients or parameters.
That is, after finding the optimum parameters,
a feature X with the weight Theta one close to zero has
a smaller effect on the prediction than features with large absolute values of Theta one.
Indeed, it allows us to understand the impact an independent variable
has on the dependent variable while controlling other independent variables.
Let's look at our dataset again.
We defined the independent variables as X and dependent variable as Y.
Notice, that for the sake of simplicity we can code
the target or dependent values to zero or one.
The goal of logistic regression is to build a model to predict
the class of each sample which in this case is a customer,
as well as the probability of each sample belonging to a class.
Given that, let's start to formalize the problem.
X is our dataset in the space of real numbers of m by n. That is,
of m dimensions or features and n records.
Y is the class that we want to predict,
which can be either zero or one.
Ideally, a logistic regression model so-called Y hat
can predict that the class of the customer is one,
given its features X.
It can also be shown quite easily that
the probability of a customer being in class zero can
be calculated as one minus the probability that the class of the customer is one.
Thanks for watching this video.